Welcome to AP US History Unit 5. This
unit covers the time period 1844 to 1877
in American history, and it's worth a
fair amount on your AP exam. As is the
same with all my other unit review
videos, this video is simply a clip
together video of all my unit 5 topic
review videos without the AP style
questions at the end of each video. If
you want to try some AP style questions
associated with each topic of unit 5, my
full unit 5 playlist is in the
description. As always, these videos
take a lot of effort to make, so if
you'd be so sweet and become a channel
member, I'd be very appreciative.
Anyway, let's get into unit 5. All
right, it is the 1840s and Americans are
looking west. This idea that Americans
deserve and are destined to expand
across the entire continent, that is
something known and called manifest
destiny and it was very popular in this
time period. So, the big question is
why? Why did Americans think they were
destined to expand? Well, simply because
land equaled opportunity. The West had
resources, open land, and the chance to
get rich. Farmers saw fertile soil.
Miners chase gold. And religious groups
like the Mormons just wanted to be left
alone in Utah. And if you want a city to
blame on that, you can look at Salt Lake
City. So, people just started packing up
and heading west. And when I say heading
west, I mean thousands of settlers
risking their lives on trails like the
Oregon Trail. Imagine walking 2,000 mi,
losing half of your wagon, fighting off
dissentry, and all you get in the end is
a nice view. But hey, for many it was
actually worth it. And that leads to the
one image that will always forever be
used to define manifest destiny. I mean,
look at that angel. It's as if these
people were meant to expand west. Or at
least that's what they thought at the
time. And the funny part is the
government wanted in on the expansion,
too. To help settlers, they passed the
Homestead Act, basically handing out
free land. that is if you could survive
on it and the Pacific Railroad Act which
helped build railroads across the
country. This made it way easier to move
west but the US wasn't just looking
west. They were looking transnational.
Americans wanted more trade with Asia
and in classic US fashion they weren't
exactly subtle about it. The Treaty of
I'm not even going to try and pronounce
that opened up trade with China and the
Treaty of Kagawa forced Japan to open
its ports to American ships. I know I've
said a million times that expansion
westward would cause the Civil War, but
before the Civil War, it will actually
cause a revolution and another war. But
that is a next video. So, it's 1845 and
James K. Pulk is elected president. If
there is one thing you should know about
this guy, it is that he cared only about
one thing, westward expansion. He
started by negotiating with Britain to
secure Oregon up to the 49th parallel.
This would avoid war while expanding the
US northwest. But here's the thing. As
America expanded, tensions with Mexico
escalated over the Texas border. The US
claimed the Rio Grande, while Mexico
insisted it was the new Cass River. Pulk
sent troops into the disputed Texas
Mexico border, and after a skirmish, he
claimed, quote, "American blood was shed
on American soil." He used this as a
justification to declare war in what was
known as the MexicanAmerican War. After
the US captures some major cities and
blockades Mexico, which cripples its
economy, they end up winning the war.
This war would end with the treaty of
Guadalupe Helago in 1848. And while this
treaty did a lot of things, what you
should know is that it gave the US a lot
of land. Like a lot of land. This land
was known as the Mexican session. And
the issue of whether each state would be
slave or free would need to be solved
further at something known as the
compromise of 1850. It should also be
noted that US interaction and conflict
with American Indians and
Mexican-Americans would increase because
of the westward expansion. These often
resulted in many unfair treaties or in
the case of San Creek, it would lead to
a bloody massacre where hundreds were
said to have been slaughtered in 1864.
On the Mexican-American War just ended,
and the US gained a massive chunk of
land. This land was known as the Mexican
session. But here's the issue. Should
slavery be allowed in this new land or
not? The North proclaimed no. The South,
however, said yes. So, yeah, we have
another political crisis. There was an
attempt to settle this issue early with
something called the Wilmont Proiso.
This was a proposal to ban slavery in
all land gained from Mexico. It passed
in the House where the North had more
representation, but failed in the
Senate, where the South had enough power
to block it. This failure only made
sectional tensions worse, pushing the
country closer to conflict. So, what
would attempt to solve this issue would
be the compromise of 1850, but it was in
many ways a messy last ditch attempt to
keep the country from falling apart. The
guy behind it, you guessed it, Henry
Clay. This compromise had five parts and
they all tried to balance free and slave
state interests. First was California
would become a free state. Second is
that Utah and New Mexico territories got
to decide on slavery themselves through
voting. Third is that the slave trade
was banned in Washington DC. Fourth was
a stricter fugitive slave act was passed
forcing northerners to return escaped
slaves. And five, Texas got paid $10
million to give up some land claims.
Yeah, I don't really understand that one
either. The big part to know about this
is the Fugitive Slave Act made
northerners furious. Even if they
weren't abolitionists, they hated being
forced to return enslaved people. This
led to massive resistance, like the
Underground Railroad working overtime
and northern states passing personal
liberty laws to ignore the act
altogether. Meanwhile, in the South,
even though they got some wins from the
compromise, they still weren't happy.
They wanted an even bigger guarantee
that slavery would expand. The failure
of this compromise was easy to see, and
this weak compromise is easily the
biggest cause of the civil war we have
talked about thus far. already know from
the entirety of unit 4 that the north
and south at this time were essentially
two different countries with the north
being industry-based and the south being
farming reliant. So now stuff is going
to happen in Europe. A series of
revolutions break out in Europe around
1848 and a potato famine breaks out in
Ireland which causes tons of immigrants
from Ireland and Germany to flood into
the US mostly all settling in northern
cities. They built ethnic communities to
preserve their language and culture. But
not everybody welcomed them. But what
you should understand is truly how many
immigrants that came into the US. I
mean, look at this graph and its spike
there. Need I even say more? All right,
enough about migration. Let's look at
some abolitionists. Even though
abolitionists were a minority in the
North, they made a lot of noise. As
we've talked about before, Frederick
Douglas gave fiery speeches, including
what to the slave is the 4th of July,
exposing the hypocrisy of American
freedom. Harriet Bechau wrote the book
Uncle Tom's Cabin, exposing the horrors
of slavery, a book that was said to be
so influential that Lincoln supposedly
said it started the Civil War. Harriet
Tubman in the Underground Railroad
helped enslaved people escaped to the
North. The North and South weren't just
disagreeing. They were on completely
different planets at this point.
Immigration, economic divide, and the
fight over slavery kept deepening
sectional conflict, making war almost
inevitable. So, it's truly time to
examine the causes of the Civil War. At
this point, every compromise about
slavery has flopped. The Missouri
Compromise gone. The Compromise of 1850
made things worse. So, now let's look at
the final attempts to hold this broken
country together and how they
spectacularly failed. The Kansas
Nebraska Act got passed, which allowed
those states to freely vote on whether
they wanted to allow slavery or not. And
the funny part, that whole Missouri
Compromise line from earlier, it didn't
matter anymore because Nebraska was well
above that line. But what you should
know about this act is it caused
thousands to pour into these states to
vote for their own side which led to
what is called bleeding Kansas where
everyone fought in the streets and
killed each other over votes in Kansas.
One of the people famous here was an
absolutely insane man named John Brown
who was against slavery and staged a
slave rebellion at Harper's Ferry before
being killed by the expertise of Robert
E. Lee. The chaos of bleeding Kansas and
the spread of slavery and enraged
anti-slavery northerners leading to the
formation of the Republican party in
1854. But now that we have all this,
let's contextualize and envision the
world right now. We know from the
Constitution that the US needs three
branches of government to function. So
let's look at each of them right now.
First, the executive. Leading up to the
Civil War, we see a collection of weak
presidents that did nothing truly
notable to address the issue of slavery.
Okay, so the executive branch is a
no-go, but let's try the legislative.
Well, here in the Senate, Charles Ser
gave a speech against slavery, which
caused a southern congressman named
Preston Brooks to beat him within an
inch of his life with a cane. Okay, so
the legislative is a bust, but as long
as we had the Supreme Court, Dread Scott
be Sanford. God damn it. This case
established that slaves were not
citizens and Congress could not ban
slavery in southern territories. So we
have the executive branch being weak. We
have people caning each other on the
Senate floor in the legislative and
deplorable, sadistic rulings by the
Supreme Court. When you look at it this
way, it honestly is hard to think a war
couldn't have broken out. And I'll end
this video with a quote from the most
sane, reasonable, level-headed guy I can
think of, John Brown. Right before he
died, he said, quote, "I am now quite
certain that the crimes of this guilty
land will never be purged away, but with
blood." And guess what? He was right.
Because the Civil War started less than
2 years later. The stage is set. America
is on the brink of collapse. The North
and the South are done with compromises.
Sectional tensions are at an all-time
high. And now there's a presidential
election that's about to decide the fate
of the entire nation. America was so
divided at this point that four
different candidates ran for president.
First we have Abraham Lincoln for the
Republican party. He was against slavery
spreading westward but not planning to
abolish it in the south. Next you have
Steven Douglas who was a northern
Democrat. His idea was to leave
decisions in the hand of the people to
vote for. Then we have John C. Breenidge
who was a southern democrat. He was very
pro-slavery wanting it everywhere. And
finally we have John Bell with the
constitutional union party who pleaded
for the constitution. Ah who cares? But
the real issue, Lincoln's Republican
party was based entirely in the North,
and he wasn't even on the ballot in 10
southern states. But guess what? It
didn't even matter. He won anyway. The
moment Lincoln won, the South absolutely
lost its mind. They saw it as the
beginning of the end for slavery. South
Carolina didn't wait around. It seceded
just weeks after the election. By early
1861, six more states followed, forming
the Confederate States of America, with
Jefferson Davis as their president.
Lincoln ran on a campaign that had at
its forefront to keep the Union
together. He promised not to invade the
South unless it was necessary to fulfill
that. In April, the Confederates decided
to enact the final straw and fired at
Fort Sumpter, a US military base in
South Carolina. Lincoln called for
troops to put down the rebellion. And
just like that, civil war had begun. So,
Lincoln is elected, the South secedes,
and war is officially started. But
here's the issue. The Union and
Confederacy were nowhere near evenly
matched. The North had more people, more
industry, more railroads, and the
ability to outproduce and outlast the
South. The only thing the South really
had was better generals and a homefield
advantage. But don't discount this part.
The South had a population that was
willing to fight to the death, and
that's where the term a war of attrition
truly comes from. The first shots were
fired at Fort Sumpter, where the
Confederacy bombarded a US fort in South
Carolina. Lincoln responded by calling
for troops, and just like that, the war
had begun. But let's be clear, the Union
was not prepared. The first major battle
at Bull Run ended with a humiliating
Union defeat, proving this war wouldn't
be over quickly. So now we see two
different war strategies unfold. The
Confederacy's plan was simple. Hold out,
play defense, and hope Europe
intervenes. Meanwhile, the Union
launched the Anaconda Plan, a strategy
to blockade the South, control the
Mississippi River, and squeeze the
Confederacy into submission. The early
war saw Confederate victories, mostly
thanks to Robert E. Lee and Stonewall
Jackson outmaneuvering Union forces.
Battles like Second Bowl Run,
Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, what
the heck are these cities showed that
the South had a real shot at winning.
Meanwhile, both sides struggled on the
home front. The New York City draft
riots showed anti-war sentiment in the
North, while the Richmond bread riots
exposed the starvation and desperation
of the South. But then comes the turning
point, 1863. First, we have the Battle
of Gettysburg, where Lee tried to go on
the offensive, but got absolutely
pummeled in a 3-day blood bath, forcing
him to retreat. And around the same
time, Ulissiz Srant won the Battle of
Vixsburg, giving the Union complete
control of the Mississippi River and
splitting the Confederacy in half. So
now the war completely shifts. Grant is
promoted and he brings in William uh
Sherman, who introduces something known
as total war. This guy truly was
unbelievable. Sherman burned everything
in his path through Georgia, destroying
crops, railroads, and entire cities in
his quote march to the sea. Meanwhile,
Grant takes on Lee directly, hammering
the Confederates with non-stop battles.
knowing that the North could replace
soldiers, but the South really couldn't.
By 1865, the South was done. Lee
surrendered at the courthouse. And just
like that, the Civil War was over. In
the end,
698,000 people died. This makes the
Civil War the deadliest war in American
history. And no, we are not counting
World War I or two in that. We talked
about all the military stuff of the
Civil War. Now, let's examine the
political side. At first, Lincoln made
it clear this war was about preserving
the Union, not ending slavery. But as
the war dragged on, that changed. Let's
talk about how. By 1862, Lincoln knew
the war needed a new purpose. And after
the Union sort of victory at Antitoum,
he issued the Emancipation Proclamation.
This document freed enslaved people in
Confederate held territories, but not in
border states. It reframed the war as a
fight against slavery, not just union
preservation. And third, it kept Europe,
especially Britain and France, from
recognizing the Confederacy. Now, even
though it didn't immediately free all
enslaved people, it was a gamecher
because now thousands of formerly
enslaved people escaped plantations and
enlisted in the Union Army. By the end
of this war, nearly 200,000
African-Americans fought for the Union.
The first South Carolina volunteer
infantry regiment and the 54th
Massachusetts proved black soldiers were
essential to the Union victory. After
the blood bath at Gettysburg, Lincoln
gave a two-minute speech that completely
redefined the Civil War. In it he said
number one the war was about preserving
democracy and fulfilling the ideals of
the founding fathers and number two the
union must win so government of the
people by the people for the people
shall not perish from the earth. This
speech solidified that America wasn't
just fighting the south. It was fighting
for its identity. But I want you to
think beyond the political aspect for a
second. For black Americans all around
the country this wasn't about some
simple politics. This was about having
the simple human right to live freely.
This is about being able to be treated
with just some dignity in their life.
This war was about freedom, democracy,
and most of all, national unity. The
civil war is over. So many battles of
attrition along with various scorched
earth policies have caused the South to
be in ruins, literally. Yes, the South
had lost the war, but now they were a
part of the Union again. So, the
government tried to usher in an era
known as reconstruction to rebuild the
South. Originally during the war,
Lincoln issued his 10% plan that told
the South he would readmit a southern
state to the Union and give it America's
protection and benefit so long as 10% of
the voters pledge loyalty to him.
Lincoln's plan aimed to be lenient and
avoid punishing the South, focusing on
restoring the Union quickly. But then
Lincoln had to go and die in 1865 by
John Wils Booth, which upset quite a
bit. Andrew Johnson came in and gave his
plan, which was very similar to Lincoln,
apart from offering pardons to former
Confederates. Then later in
reconstruction, the radical Republican
plan was put into effect as Republicans
gained more power. This was meant to
punish the South, protect black rights,
and send the military to enforce it. The
South absolutely hated this. And the
thing is, Andrew Johnson hated radical
Republicans and tried to veto
everything. Congress responded by
impeaching him, making him the first US
president to almost be removed from
office. Reconstruction also allowed some
amendments to be passed as well. the
13th amendment which abolished slavery,
the 14th, which granted birthright
citizenship and equal protection under
the law, and the 15th, which gave black
men the right to vote. But even though
this seems like a good idea, you need to
understand that this era was really no
better for African-Americans than before
the Civil War. Almost immediately after
the southern states were readmitted to
the Union, they passed black codes,
which were codes in the South that
limited freedoms of African-Americans
and continuously forced
African-Americans into forced labor.
Despite slavery being technically over,
blacks worked the fields in a system
known as sharecropping where it wasn't
technically slave labor, but with their
wages it might as well have been. There
would be public events held in the south
where people would gather to watch
African-Americans be hanged or [\h__\h] and
feathered or any number of ways to die
known as lynchings. And then you have
organizations like the Ku Klux Clan and
the White League which used literal
terrorism to suppress black voters. All
of this would force the North to just
give up entirely and cause
reconstruction to fail. But that is a
next video. So reconstruction was
supposed to fix the South and bring
equality for all African-Americans, but
instead it completely failed. At first,
things looked promising. Black men
gained citizenship and voting rights.
Over 2,000 African-Americans held public
office and federal troops were stationed
in the South to enforce reconstruction
policies, but white southerners hated
this and they fought back hard. We
already talked about some examples of
this being sharecropping, lynchings, and
organizations like the KKK, but you also
had things like convict leasing, where
black men were arrested for madeup
crimes and forced into unpaid labor.
Then came the Supreme Court, which
basically gave up on protecting black
rights. The slaughterhouse cases in 1873
gutted the 14th Amendment by saying
civil rights were a state issue, not a
federal one. In the US, v that they said
that the federal government couldn't
punish white mobs that murdered black
Americans. With no one left to enforce
black rights, white southerners took
control again. And then came the final
nail in the coffin, being the compromise
of 1877. Essentially, the 1876
presidential election was a mess. So,
Republicans and Democrats made a
backroom deal. The North would remove
troops from the South, and in return,
they would elect a Republican Rutherford
Be Hayes as president. But this would
mean reconstruction would end, and the
South could do whatever it wanted. So,
that's exactly what happened. Black
rights were crushed for nearly a
century. Jim Crow laws, segregation, and
voter suppression took over.
Reconstruction was the US's first
attempt at civil rights, and it failed
miserably. But the 14th and 15th
Amendments didn't go away. They became
the legal foundation for the civil
rights movement 100 years later. Just
like that, unit 5 is done.
Reconstruction has ended and nothing bad
happens in American history ever again.
Right. Anyway, why don't you subscribe
to this YouTube channel? It's my
non-educational channel and I promise
it's a thousand% cooler than this one.
Come on, please. Please.
[Music]